hey there and welcome back to heimlich's
history it is ap exam season and i've
been publishing a bunch of videos to
help you get ready in the last video i
showed you my process for writing a dbq
for ap
world history but you didn't think i was
going to leave my a push students behind
did you he was so crazy so in this video
i'm going to show you how to write a dbq
from beginning to end for ap
us history so if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked well then let's
get to it so if you're not already
familiar with the rubric for the dbq
you're going to need to start there and
this video right here will make all your
dreams come true in this video i'm going
to assume that you know
all the scoring requirements of the
essay and so what i'm going to do here
is to take you through the process that
i would go through from the moment i
first saw the prompt to the moment i
start writing in other words
i'm going to show you how i plan for the
dbq and a good plan almost always means
a good essay so do not hurry through
this get these principles firmly shoved
into your brain fold so you can do it
without thinking i'm going to be using
this planning guide right here that i
created if you want to follow along with
me
you can get that in the link in the
description also it's going to be
helpful if you have the dbq itself which
you can also find
at the link in the description below as
i said in the other video this isn't the
only way to do it maybe it's not even
the best way but this is the process
that makes sense to me and so if you
know a better way to do it a method that
makes more sense to you well then you do
that but for the rest of you i just
recommend doing what i'm about to show
you now to be clear you can't have this
dbq worksheet on the exam so it's good
to practice a lot and get the principles
down so it's second nature by the time
you sit for the exam
all right let's get into the dbq all
right let's begin by looking at the
prompt evaluate the relative importance
of different causes for the expanding
role of the united states in the world
in the period from 1865 to 1910. okay so
now i'm going to go over to my worksheet
and just make sure i understand
everything they're asking me in the
prompt because that's the first step to
really nailing your essay evaluate the
relative importance of different
causes what's the historical thinking
skill it is causation but the causes of
what what is it asking you about
in this case it's the expanding role of
the united states and the world
and let's not forget it's not just
asking me about the causes of the
expanding role of the united states in
the world it's asking me about the
relative importance of the different
causes
in other words there's going to be some
causes that are more important some
causes that are less important and it's
up to me as the one writing this essay
to establish which of them are more
important which are less important okay
now the time period just to make sure i
don't forget where i'm writing and that
is 1865 to 1910.
okay i think i have a pretty good
understanding of what they're asking me
to do in this prompt and so now let's go
back and read the documents
all right i'm not going to read all
these documents too you might just want
to pause this
and read them for yourself and take a
few minutes to do that but i'm just
going to show you
the key things that i'm taking out of
these documents so in document 1 the
first thing i see is that what we're
about to read is a treaty
and after reading the whole thing it
really is just an explanation
of russia ceding their north american
territory to the united states so this
is a document
about land session okay moving on to
document two it's from josiah strong
from a book called our country its
possible future in present crisis
1885. first of all i noticed that he
invokes
the divine to talk about the anglo-saxon
race he talks about the final
competition of races for which the
anglo-saxon
is being schooled then he has a great
opinion of the anglo-saxon race this
race of unequaled energy he uses words
like
majesty and if josiah's strong was to
have his way the anglo-saxon race will
spread itself
over the earth now this document also
seems to have something to do with
lands as well the lands of the earth are
limited he says
and that's what the competition of the
races is going to be about so maybe this
is another document about land
but the race thing really dominates this
so i'm going to put it in that category
i'm just going to write over here racial
destiny because remember what we're
trying to do is understand these
documents in the context of the prompt
and the prompt is about the expanding
role of the united states in the world
so the first document has something to
do with the gaining of
land the second one has to do with like
racial superiority so
that's where we're headed okay document
number three is by captain alfred thayer
mahan
the interest of america in sea power
present and future and the first thing
he mentions is the importance of distant
markets he mentions the
american influence in places like the
caribbean in central america but then he
mentions a problem
we have not the navy and what is worse
we are not willing to have the navy so
this tells me there's something about
economics going on here and the
relationship of having a good navy to
protecting economic interest
so i'm going to put economics right here
all these words that i'm writing off to
the side are going to help me later with
my grouping okay document number four
has president william mckinley serving
uncle sam and he's saying well i hardly
know which to take first in reference to
all of these places up here and the only
other thing i want to do on this
document is just to notice this date
1898 that makes me think of something
and hopefully it makes you think of
something else as well and that's going
to help me later in my sourcing
it makes me think of the
spanish-american war it's probable that
i'm later going to use that for sourcing
so i just want to make a note of it so i
don't forget
document 5 is from john hay who is the
secretary of state and this is the
second open door note in 1900. what i
see here is that he wants to protect
the economic interests of the united
states in china but there's a problem
which he calls the condition at peaking
and
it's one of virtual anarchy and what he
wants to secure is impartial trade with
all parts of the chinese empire so again
that tells me that what we're looking at
is a document that is economic in nature
i'm going to write right here
economics but then if i'm really on my
game i'm going to source this for
historical context because
this condition at peaking is actually
the boxer rebellion so i just want to
make a note of that there so i can use
it later alright the next document comes
from puck which i want to notice
is a satirical magazine which means
whatever i'm about to see in this
picture is a criticism of the reality
that it depicts
and so here we have uncle sam and he's
holding a soldier right here and a
teacher right here
over here he's talking to native
filipinos i see that right here and he
says to them you can take your choice i
have plenty of both
so really all i want to take from this
document is that uncle sam seems to be
offering the filipinos the option to
either be conquered by force or by
assimilation
this seems to fit into the racial
category so i just want to note that
there and move on and then finally we
need to look at document seven this is
from president theodore roosevelt his
fourth annual message to congress
in 1904. okay now this is an interesting
document because he says
it is not true that the united states
feels any land hunger which actually
directly contradicts what we saw
in that image in document 4. so i'm just
going to note that contradiction in my
mind because that could be interesting
to work in for complexity all roosevelt
wants is to see
the neighboring country stable orderly
and prosperous and if they're not that
ultimately means that they will require
intervention by some civilized nation
and the exercise of an international
police power now hopefully if you've
been studying that's going to remind you
of something what this is called is the
roosevelt corollary to the monroe
doctrine so i'm just going to write that
here to remind myself to use it for
sourcing
okay so that's just a quick
interpretation of all the documents now
what i've done
is in my document section of my
worksheet i've just given a
brief one or two sentence one or two
phrase description of each document
that's not everything in the documents
but it is enough to jog my memory and
give me a brief idea of what they're
about so now what i want to do before we
move on to the back is i just want to
fill out a few of these other boxes just
to make sure i get all my points
i put this outside evidence column right
here not because you need that many
pieces of outside evidence you actually
only need
one but because this is the way it works
for me for me as i'm reading the
documents that will often jog my memory
as you saw before when we were dealing
with the documents of something that i
could use for outside evidence and so
when i was reading about russia's
seating territory to the u.s that
reminded me of what it was called namely
seward's folly that might be something i
can expand upon for outside evidence or
maybe i could use it for sourcing but
i'm just gonna put it in this box for
now and then when i was reading document
two what i really thought about was
frederick
jackson turner's frontier thesis so i'm
just making a note right now of what i
thought of when i read the documents and
i will choose which one i'm gonna use
later so now let's go to the sourcing
section and when i was reading document
2 that made me think of the
historical context of social darwinism
and then as i mentioned as i was reading
document 4 that reminded me of the
historical context of the
spanish-american war
and then when i was reading document 5
again historical context
that made me think of the boxer
rebellion
all right so that's everything i need to
do for this front section let's flip it
over and keep working the next thing i
want to work on
is the grouping of the documents and the
reason why we do this do not skip this
the reason why we do this
is so that it sets us up for an argument
we have to group the documents we don't
just want to list the documents one
after another because that is a sure
sign
that you're not making an argument so
let's group these documents the
groupings that i came up with were as
follows i saw
one four seven two and six
and then three and five one four and
seven seem to have land in common so i'm
going to title that category manifest
destiny
documents two and six seem to have
something to do about race so i'm gonna
name that
race and then documents three and five
had to do with economics
okay so these are three causes of the
expanding role of the united states in
the world you've got manifest destiny or
hunger for land you've got race and
you've got economics okay so
remember our goal is to evaluate the
relative importance of these causes
which one is the most
important and as i was reading and
trying to make sense of the evidence it
seemed to me that the most important
cause was going to be
land hunger or manifest destiny and so
now i'm just going to write my topic
sentences this is going to be the first
sentence of each of my body paragraphs
so my topic sentence would be the most
important cause of the expanding role of
the united states in the world is the
long-held belief of manifest destiny
and then i would do something similar
for the other two so once i've got my
topic sentences down i've got my groups
established the thesis
kind of almost writes itself that's why
we leave the thesis to this point so
let's do that remember the thesis
formula is although
x because a and b therefore y why is the
counter argument
a and b is your specific historical
evidence and why is your argument so
here's what i'd write although racial
superiority and the desire for overseas
markets were important causes in
america's imperialist ventures
because of the sheer amount of land
acquisition including alaska hawaii and
the philippines
the notion of manifest destiny was the
most important cause of the expanding
role of the united states
from 1865 to 1910. all right it's not
beautiful it's a little bit clunky
it's not the most elegantly written
thing you've ever seen however it
is complex and it does set me up for an
argumentative essay okay now that i have
my thesis i can decide
what i want to use to contextualize that
argument that's why the
contextualization part is here so
remember our contextualization has to
relate to the argument we're making in
our essay so i'm going to talk about
land acquisition i'm going to talk about
race
and i'm going to talk about economics so
i want to contextualize those three
things again what i'm about to do is
probably more than you need but just fyi
here's how i would do it to
contextualize land acquisition and
manifest destiny i want to talk about
westward expansion
specifically i want to mention oregon
texas and the mexican session
then to contextualize the economics
argument i want to talk about
commodore matthew perry and his opening
of japan to trade
and then to contextualize the racial
issue i'm thinking of
rudyard kipling's white man's burden and
of course kipling was an englishman not
an american
but that does put it in the larger
context of the
worldwide colonial ventures of the time
so the last thing i want to do in this
section is i want to make sure to force
myself to connect these to my argument
so i'm going to make sure to tie this to
land acquisition trade and economics and
racial dominance okay now the last thing
i need to do in all of this is make sure
i write down what i'm going to use for
my evidence beyond the documents now i
gave myself a couple of options on the
other side of the page
when we talked about the documents i'm
going to choose frederick jackson
turner's
frontier thesis so in my essay i'm going
to name
the frontier thesis i'm going to tell
what it is
and the last thing i want to do is make
sure i connect it to the larger
argument that i'm making so in this case
the larger argument is that
turner argued that expansion into other
territories is
basically baked into the dna of
americans and so once the frontier was
closed
we had to go elsewhere we had to expand
our role in the world all right that's
all the planning from there you just
start writing all the pieces are in
place and if you follow this procedure
and do it well then you will be on your
way to earning a good score on the dbq
all right that was a lot and if you're
still here after all of that then thank
you for sticking around and i hope that
was helpful and if you need even more
help on your essays then click right
over here grab my apsa cram course and
if you want more videos like this then
you can let me know by subscribing
heimler out